<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE refentry PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.3//EN" 
               "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.3/docbookx.dtd" [
<!ENTITY igraph "<command>igraph</command>">
]>

<chapter id="igraph-introduction">
<title>Introduction</title>

<para>
This is another library for creating and manipulating graphs. There
is simply no other graph library out there which can be handle
graphs of the size the author is confronted with
efficiently. Whenever possible <command>igraph</command> tries to be also user
friendly and portable.
</para>

<para>
<command>igraph</command> started as an additional package to the GNU R
statistical environment, and still some functions which are hard to
implement in C are available only in R (like interactive
graphics). Most functions are however now written in C and they can
be compiled without R as a separate library. Still the author
highly recommends R, as it is a sophisticated, well desinged,
modern system.
</para>

<para>
The advantage of the C version is that it is portable, can
be used with other mathematical software (as soon as somebody
writes the interfaces to it), and can be used for large scale
scientific computation in the Condor environment we are
using here at KFKI.
</para>

<para>
<command>igraph</command> also features a Python interface, and other interfaces
can be added without too much pain.
</para>

<section><title>Features</title>

<itemizedlist>
<listitem><para><command>igraph</command> contains functions for generating regular and
  random graphs according to known algorithms and models in the
  network theory literature. </para></listitem>
<listitem><para><command>igraph</command> provides routines for manipulating graphs,
  adding and removing edges and vertices. </para></listitem>
<listitem><para>a set of structural property calculation functions like
  degree, betweenness, etc. are also included. </para></listitem>
<listitem><para>force based layout generators are included for smaller graphs,
  another method is expected to be added for large graphs
  soon.</para></listitem> 
<listitem><para>a set of conversion functions are also included and will be
  extended shortly.</para></listitem>
<listitem><para><command>igraph</command> iterators provide a simple and efficient way
  of walking through graphs.</para></listitem>
<listitem><para><command>igraph</command> is well documented both for users and
  developers.</para></listitem> 
<listitem><para><command>igraph</command> is open source and distributed under GNU
  GPL.</para></listitem> 
</itemizedlist>
</section>

<section><title><command>igraph</command> is free software</title>
<para>
    IGraph library
</para><para>
    Copyright (C) 2003, 2004, 2005  Gabor Csardi &lt;csardi@rmki.kfki.hu>
    MTA RMKI, Konkoly-Thege Miklos st. 29-33, Budapest 1121, Hungary
</para><para>
    This program is free software; you can redistribute it and/or modify
    it under the terms of the GNU General Public License as published by
    the Free Software Foundation; either version 2 of the License, or
    (at your option) any later version.
</para><para>
    This program is distributed in the hope that it will be useful,
    but WITHOUT ANY WARRANTY; without even the implied warranty of
    MERCHANTABILITY or FITNESS FOR A PARTICULAR PURPOSE.  See the
    GNU General Public License for more details.
</para><para>
    You should have received a copy of the GNU General Public License
    along with this program; if not, write to the Free Software
    Foundation, Inc., 59 Temple Place, Suite 330, Boston, MA  02111-1307  USA
</para>
</section>

<section><title>Citing <command>igraph</command></title>
<para>
To cite <command>igraph</command> in publications, please use the following
reference:
</para><para>
Gábor Csárdi, Tamás Nepusz: The igraph software package for complex network
research. InterJournal Complex Systems, 1695, 2006.
</para>

</section>

</chapter>
