<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.3//EN" 
               "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.3/docbookx.dtd" [
<!ENTITY igraph "<application>igraph</application>">
]>

<chapter id="igraphbook-datamodel">
<title>The igraph data model</title>

<para>
This section introduces the &igraph; data model. It is recommended
that the reader should be familiar with this model of computation to
understand the semantics of the &igraph; functions better.
</para>

<para>
An &igraph; graph is either <glossterm>directed</glossterm> or
<glossterm>undirected</glossterm>, &igraph; cannot handle mixed graphs
with both directed and undirected edges.
</para>

<section><title>Directed graphs</title>

<para>
The &igraph; data model is slightly different for directed and
undirected graphs, we start with the directed case. In &igraph;
vertices are identified by <glossterm>vertex id</glossterm>s: integer
number between zero and |V|-1, if |V| is the number of vertices in the
graph. Thus the numbering of vertex ids is always continual, all
&igraph; operations on graphs keep this important property. 
</para>

<para>
Directed &igraph; edges are ordered pairs or vertex ids. A directed
graph is an ordered multiset of directed edges and some additional
meta data: the number of vertices in the graph and whether the graph
is directed. Here is an example of a directed &igraph; graph:
<informalexample>
<programlisting>
  ( vertices: 6, 
    directed: yes,
    {
     (0,2),
     (2,2),
     (2,3),
     (3,3),
     (3,4),
     (3,4),
     (4,1)
    }
  )
</programlisting>
</informalexample>
</para>

<para>
Just like the vertices have vertex ids, &igraph; edges also have ids:
edge ids are integer numbers between zero and |E|-1, |E| is the number
of edges in the graph. 
</para>

</section>

<section><title>Undirected graphs</title>

<para>
An undirected &igraph; edge is a two-element or one-element set of
vertex ids. The two element set is a non-loop edge, ie. the edge
connects different vertices, while loop edges are represented with a
single-element set. An undirected graph is an ordered multiset of
undirected edges, plus the usual meta data: the number of vertices and
the fact that the graph is undirected. Here is an example for an
undirected graph:
<informalexample>
<programlisting>
  ( vertices: 6,
    directed: no,
    {
     {0,2},
     {2},
     {2,3},
     {3},
     {3,4},
     {3,4},
     {4,1}
    }
  )
</programlisting>
</informalexample>
This graph contains both loop edges ({2} and {3}, ie. (2-2) and (3-3))
and multiple edges ({3,4} twice). 
</para>

</section>

</chapter>
